A Guide to the Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers, 1929-1998
Washington and Lee University, School of Law, Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives
- Professional Associations 1937-1971
  - Virginia State Bar Association 1948-1970
    - Committees
      - Executive
        - Correspondence, 1956-1960 (Box-folder 236/10-16)
        - Minutes, 1956-1960 (Box-folder 236/17-19)
      - Junior Bar, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 236/20-21)
      - Economics of Law Practice, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 236/22-25)
      - Law Students, 1970 (Box-folder 236/26-30)
      - Legal Aid and Reference, 1956 (Box-folder 237/1)
      - Library, Legal Records and Legal Literature, 1949-1952 (Box-folder 237/2)
    - Printed Materials 1950-1970 (Box-folder 237/3)
- Federal Commissions, Panels, and Conferences 1948-1971
  - Special Assistant to the Attorney General re Selective Service 1948-1952
    This series includes two folders of general correspondence and a dozen case files. Attorney General Tom Clark appointed Powell Special Assistant to the Attorney General to act in the Eastern District of Virginia as Hearing Officer under section 6 (j) of the Selective Service Act of 1948. In this unpaid capacity, Powell was to help in determining "the character and good faith" of those registrants claiming to be conscientiously opposed to participation in war.
    - Correspondence, 1948-1952 (Box-folder 237/4-5)
    - Case Files, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 237/6--17)
  - Joint Civilian Defense Orientation Conference 1957-1958
    Joint Civilian Defense Orientation Conference is three inches of correspondence and printed materials concerning Powell's participation in this May 2-11, 1957 conference. Selected civilians were flown to various U.S. military bases where they witnessed demonstrations and exercises. The aim was to give the conferees an overall acquaintance with the national defense program and to invite their views on the defense effort.
    - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 237/18)
    - Printed Materials
      - Schedules and Instructions, 1957 (Box-folder 237/19)
      - Background Materials, 1957 (Box-folder 237/20)
      - Clippings, 1957 (Box-folder 237/21)
      - Memorabilia, 1957 (Box-folder 237/22)
  - Attorney General's Conference on Court Congestion and Delay In Litigation 1958-1960
    Attorney General's Conference on Court Congestion and Delay In Litigation is one inch of correspondence and printed materials concerning Powell's work on this conference, created by the Attorney General of the United States. The aim of this group was to generate ideas and lend support to legislative efforts designed to improve the administration of justice. State committees were formed to support more day-to-day activities, and Powell also served on the Virginia committee.
    - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 237/23)
    - Printed Materials, 1959 (Box-folder 237/24)
  - President's Commission On Law Enforcement and Administration of Justice 1965-1967 (Box 89-90)
    President's Commission On Law Enforcement and Administration of Justice(1.75 cu.ft.) begins with a record volume comprising correspondence, memoranda, report drafts, and a printed copy of the supplemental statement to the commission's report. Some of the contents of this volume are duplicated in the unbound records that follow. These other records include subseries of correspondence, memoranda, notes, chapter drafts of the report, drafts of the supplemental statement and a printed version of the report. Miscellaneous documents, printed materials, and clippings complete the series.
    Based on the awareness of the crime problem that Powell had articulated in many of his speeches as ABA President, President Johnson appointed Powell to this commission. Though this diverse committee agreed on many solutions to the crime problem, there were differences among the commissioners. Powell's differing views on the questions of wire tapping and certain Supreme Court decisions led to his drafting of the "Supplemental Statement on Constitutional Limitations," published over the names of seven commission members.
    Powell anticipated criticism of the inconsistencies between the views expressed in his work on this commission and some of his Supreme Court opinions. In an annotation (written after Powell was appointed to the Supreme Court) to the introduction to the record volume in this series he wrote, "When I accepted appointment to this Commission I knew little criminal law as I never practiced it... and some of my views have changed."
    - Record Volume, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 238/1)
      Selected correspondence, memoranda and commission reports bound by the donor.
    - Correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 238/2-15, Box-folder 239/1-9)
    - Memoranda, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 239/10-14)
    - Notes, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 239/15)
    - Notebook re Memorandum On Wiretapping, 1966 (Box-folder 239/16, Box-folder 240/1-5)
    - Report, 1966-1967
      - Draft Chapters, 1966 (Box-folder 240/6-10)
      - Drafts of Supplemental Statement, 1967 (Box-folder 240/11)
      - Report - Printed Version, 1967 (Box-folder 240/12)
    - Party for the Commissioners, 1966 (Box-folder 241/1)
    - Press Releases, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 241/2)
    - List of Commissioners and Staff; Miscellaneous Documents, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 241/3)
    - Printed Materials, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 241/4)
    - Clippings, 1963-1967 (Box-folder 241/5-8)
  - Blue Ribbon Defense Panel 1969-1970
    Blue Ribbon Defense Panel (1.66 cu.ft.) contains the records of Powell's service on the commission President Nixon created to recommend reforms in the structure and operation of the Pentagon. It was to evaluate the organization and management of the Department of Defense, but not delve into questions of broad national policy. This body was formed in the face of mounting criticism of cost overruns in weapons systems and the stalemate in Vietnam.
    As in his work on the crime commission, Powell expressed his views separately from those of the panel's report. This time these expressions took two forms. The first was Powell's thirty-five page statement (signed by seven of the sixteen panelists), "Shifting Balance of Military Power." Drafts and three different printed versions are included in subseries 5.5(c) "Supplemental Statement." The other separate expression was Powell's reaction to the war in Vietnam. This was sent confidentially to President Nixon as the memorandum, "Political Warfare." A draft and final version are included under that title in the 5.4 Subject Files. (Another copy is in the "Speeches, Statements and Writings" series of the II. Personal Papers).
    Forms of materials which make up this subseries include: correspondence; memoranda; notes; subject files; drafts and printed versions of the report; and printed materials. The Commission's Southeast Asian, European and NORAD inspection trips are documented in the subject files.
    - Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 241/9-24, Box-folder 242/1-13)
    - Memoranda
      - From Panel Chair, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 242/14-17)
      - To Panel Chair, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 242/18-20)
        Some letters included in this file.
      - From Staff Coordinator, 1969 (Box-folder 242/21)
    - Notes, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 242/22-24)
    - Subject Files
      - Conflict of Interest, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 243/1-2)
      - Minutes, 1969 (Box-folder 243/3-4)
      - Political Warfare Memorandum, 1970 (Box-folder 243/5)
      - Travel Orders, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 243/6-7)
      - Questionnaire, 1969 (Box-folder 243/8-10)
      - Trips
        - European, 1969 (Box-folder 243/11)
        - Asian, 1970 (Box-folder 243/12)
        - Southeast Asian, 1970 (Box-folder 243/13-15)
        - NORAD - Army Defense Command and Aerospace Defense, 1970 (Box-folder 243/16)
    - Report
      - Chapter Drafts, April 1970-June 1970 (Box-folder 243/17-20, Box-folder 244/1)
      - Printed Version, July 1, 1970 (Box-folder 244/2)
      - Supplemental Statement
        - Notes and Rough Draft, May 1, 1970 (Box-folder 244/3)
        - Draft, September 15, 1970 (Box-folder 244/4)
        - Proofs, September 1970 (Box-folder 244/5)
        - Government Printing Office Version, September 30, 1970 (Box-folder 244/6)
        - Privately Printed Version, September 15, 1970 (Box-folder 244/7)
        - Congressional Record Version, April 19, 1971 (Box-folder 244/8)
    - Printed Materials
      - Background, 1949,1966 & 1969 (Box-folder 245/1)
      - re Report, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 245/2)
    - Clippings, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 245/3-5)
  - Advisory Commission of the Federal Judiciary Center 1971 (Box-folder 245/6)
    Advisory Commission of the Federal Judicial Center is one file consisting of a few letters about Powell's appointment to this commission. Within weeks of this appointment, Powell was nominated to the Supreme Court, effectively ending his service.
- Civic Activities 1946-1971
  Comprises the records (6.75 cu. ft.) of ten governmental and charitable organizations serving the Richmond area or the Commonwealth of Virginia, with which Powell was associated.
  - Richmond Chamber of Commerce 1946-1960
    Contains general correspondence; bylaws and minutes; and publications by the Chamber. One subseries contains Powell's papers as President of the Chamber of Commerce in 1950. These consist of correspondence; subject files; and speeches, statements and writings.
    - Correspondence, 1946-1960 (Box-folder 245/7-13)
    - By-Laws, Minutes and Miscellaneous Documents, 1946-1950 (Box-folder 245/14)
    - Publications, 1946-1955 (Box-folder 245/15-18)
    - President
      - Correspondence, 1949-1952 (Box-folder 245/19-32, Box-folder 246/1)
      - Appointment of Committees, 1950 (Box-folder 246/2-3)
      - Tax Relief in Virginia, 1950 (Box-folder 246/4)
      - Expressway Referendum, 1950 (Box-folder 246/5)
      - Speeches, Statements and Reports, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 246/6)
  - Richmond Charter Commission 1947-1957
    Made up of correspondence; speeches and statements; lists of persons who testified about the charter; and clippings. Powell's service on this commission was his only venture into electoral politics. Richmond had an ineffective form of government based on a federal model--a bicameral city council and a mayor with veto power. State law authorized the election of a charter commission to propose a new form of government, to be submitted to the electorate by referendum. Powell was elected to the Commission and chosen as chairman by his fellow commissioners. The city manager style of government proposed by the commission was enacted by referendum on November 7, 1947.
    - Correspondence, 1947-1957 (Box-folder 246/7)
    - Speeches and Statements, 1946-1948 & n.d. (Box-folder 246/8-9)
    - Lists, 1948 (Box-folder 246/10)
    - Clippings, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 246/11-17)
    - Printed Materials, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 246/18)
  - American Cancer Society -- Richmond Chapter 1949-1950 (Box-folder 246/19)
    This one folder consists of correspondence and reports.
  - Richmond School Board 1950-1962
    Anyone delving into the Richmond School Board series with the hope of finding thorough documentation of the desegregation of Richmond public schools, or of Powell's contemporaneous thoughts on desegregated education, is bound to be disappointed. There is documentation of the desegregation struggle, but it is mostly limited to newspaper clippings. There is expression of Powell's thinking on race, but it is mostly from the perspective of a 1975 Supreme Court Justice, whose social views had markedly changed in the intervening decades.
    Like the other parts of this series, the bulk of the contents of the record volume are devoted to the budgetary process, teacher salaries, raising the quality of education and the inclusion of education against communism in the school curriculum. Powell speeches on educational matters are also present.
    The titles of the various parts of the correspondence subseries mirror interests and activities noted in the record volume: General; Course on International Communism; Report on Trip to Russia; and Speech to Richmond Public School Teachers. The "Trip to Russia," in the subseries title above, was Powell's visit in the summer of 1958 with a delegation of lawyers representing the American Bar Association. They attended conferences and exchanged views with Soviet lawyers and judges. Upon his return, Powell spoke and wrote about his experiences in a variety of settings. The same month he returned from this trip, August 1958, he reported to the Richmond School Board. The Board published the report in pamphlet form under the title, "Soviet Education--A Means Towards World Domination: Report on Trip to Soviet Union (July - August 1958)." The "Trip to Russia" correspondence consists of cover letters which accompanied some of the distributed copies of the reports and thank you letters from recipients of the report.
    There are also subseries of speeches, statements, subject files, printed materials and clippings. The folder titles in the container list for the speeches, statements and subject files generally reveal their contents. The "Desegregation--General" subject file consists mostly of speeches and statements by persons other than Powell. The "Desegregation--Chandler School" subject file contains correspondence from homeowners living near that school. There is no record here of the debate at which Powell silenced the crowd trying to prevent black attorney Oliver Hill from speaking. The "Desegregation--Lawsuits" file contains documents regarding legal actions taken by "certain Negro children and their parents" in which the school board was named.
    The "Publications by Richmond Public Schools" include: City of Richmond Superintendent of Schools annual reports for the years 1950, 1951 and 1954; and the pamphlet, "Quality in Education: A National Necessity," the printed version of Powell's February 1958 address to Richmond Public School teachers.
    - Record Volume: Richmond School Board, 1950-1961, 1975 (Box-folder 247/1)
      Letters, memoranda, reports and clippings assembled and bound by Powell. Includes Powell's annotations both contemporaneous and from later periods. There is a 1975 introduction by Powell.
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1950-1961 (Box-folder 247/2-17, Box-folder 248/1-29)
      - Course On International Communism, 1958-1961 (Box-folder 248/30-31, Box-folder 249/1-7)
      - Report 0n Trip to Russia, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 249/8-12)
    - Speeches, 1953-1962
      - Remarks at School Convention, September 1, 1953 (Box-folder 249/13)
      - Remarks before Richmond First Club, December 10, 1953 (Box-folder 249/14)
      - Quality In Education, February 15, 1958 (Box-folder 249/15)
      - Speech to Richmond Public School Teachers, February 19, 1958 (Box-folder 249/16)
      - Report on Trip to Soviet Union(to Richmond School Board), August 1958 (Box-folder 249/17)
      - Excerpts from Talk to Alexandria Education Association, February 12, 1959 (Box-folder 249/18)
      - Convocation of Teachers, September 2, 1959 (Box-folder 249/19)
      - Recent Developments In the Richmond Public Schools, November 18, 1959 (Box-folder 249/20)
      - Notes on European System of Education, November 18, 1959 (Box-folder 249/21)
      - Soviet Reorganization of Public Schools, November 18, 1959 (Box-folder 249/22)
      - Notes on Religion in Richmond Public Schools, November 18, 1959 (Box-folder 249/23)
      - The Pornographic Problem In Perspective Notes for Panel Discussion Sponsored by Junior League, February 2, 1960 (Box-folder 249/24)
      - Notes on Panel Program -- Why Should Our Students Know About Communist System? Chicago, National School Boards Meeting, April 26, 1960 (Box-folder 249/25-26)
      - Comment On Admiral Rickover's Statement ... On Public Education, August 28, 1960 (Box-folder 249/27)
      - The Challenge of School Board Membership, October 7, 1960 (Box-folder 249/28-29)
      - Notes for Speech, Convocation of Richmond School Teachers, October 6, 1960 (Box-folder 249/30)
      - Notes re Education in Communism, c. 1960 (Box-folder 249/31)
      - The Need for Instruction On International Communism, January 26, 1961 (Box-folder 249/32)
        ABA Committee Conference with Educators, Washington, DC
      - Excerpts from Talk Before Southeastern Association of School and Business Officials, April 19, 1961 (Box-folder 249/33)
      - Higher Education Soviet Style, April 27, 1962 (Box-folder 249/34)
        Notes for Speech, Federal Bar Association, Washington, DC
    - Statements
      - General
        - Power of the City Council with Respect to School Funds, June 1951 (Box-folder 249/35)
        - Statement by Lewis Powell, October 27, 1952 (Box-folder 249/36)
        - Statement Given to News Leader re Brown Decision, May 18, 1954 (Box-folder 249/37)
        - Statement to Council re Teachers' Salary, December 27, 1954 (Box-folder 249/38)
        - Check-list to Determine Extent of Progress Actually Being Made in Up-Grading Education in Richmond, July 1958 (Box-folder 249/39)
        - Proposed Statement of Policy by State Board of Education with Respect to High School Curriculum, October 31, 1958 (Box-folder 249/40)
        - Supporting Construction of New High School, May 6, 1959 (Box-folder 249/41)
        - Statement to Virginia Commission on Public Education, July 14, 1959 (Box-folder 249/42)
        - Responsibilities and Powers re Conversion of School Property from White to Negro Use, July 27, 1959 (Box-folder 250/1)
        - Responsibilities of the Richmond School Board, November 4, 1959 (Box-folder 250/2)
        - Outline of Comments to The General Assembly's Commission on Public Education, November 18, 1959 (Box-folder 250/3)
          Comments by Henry I. Willett.
        - Statement before Senate Finance Committee, February 5, 1960 (Box-folder 250/4)
        - Chandler School Problem, April 22, 1960 (Box-folder 250/5)
        - Supplemental Statement to Virginia Commission On Public Education, December 13, 1960 (Box-folder 250/6)
      - re Teaching Communism 1960-1961 (Box-folder 250/7-8)
    - Subject Files
      - Audit Reports, 1950-1953 (Box-folder 250/9)
      - Budget, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 250/10)
      - Course On Communism, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 250/11-12)
        Includes memoranda and course outlines.
      - Desegregation
        - General, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 250/13)
        - Chandler School, 1960 (Box-folder 250/14)
        - Lawsuits, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 250/15)
      - Mayor's Resolution re School Building Use, 1959 (Box-folder 250/16)
      - Minutes, 1951 (Box-folder 250/17)
      - Policies, 1940, 1952-1960 & n.d. (Box-folder 250/18-21, Box-folder 251/1)
      - Pornography, 1960 (Box-folder 251/2)
      - Reports, 1951-1960 & n.d. (Box-folder 251/3-7)
        Includes 1959 Spong Report
      - School Construction, 1951, 1953 (Box-folder 251/8)
      - Teachers' Salaries, 1954-1959 (Box-folder 251/9)
    - Printed Materials
      - Publications by Richmond Public Schools, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 251/10)
      - State of Virginia Publications, 1958, 1960 (Box-folder 251/11)
      - re Soviet Education, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 251/12)
      - Miscellaneous, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 251/13)
    - Clippings
      - General 1952-1961 (Box-folder 252/1)
      - Integration 1958-1960 (Box-folder 252/2)
      - Russian v. American Education, 1953-1961 (Box-folder 252/3-5)
  - State Library Board (Virginia) 1954-1964 (Box-folder 252/6-11)
    Consists of 1.5 inches of correspondence about Powell's service on this body. Most of the letters concern notices of, and preparations for upcoming meetings.
  - Virginia Industrialization Group 1958-1964 & 1980
    Four inches of correspondence and memoranda from Powell's membership in this private group of businessmen organized to promote industrial development in the state. Also included is a June 1980 informal history of the group documenting its role in opposing massive resistance. This was written by the group's former chairman--and former Norfolk and Western Railway Company president--Stuart Saunders.
    Realizing that few businesses would come to Virginia until the school crisis was resolved, the group held a dinner meeting on December 19, 1958, attended by the Governor, Lieutenant Governor and Attorney General, at which the relationship of the school crisis to industrial development was discussed. Though Powell was out of town at the time of the meeting, his memorandum of December 15, 1958 to Saunders and vice- chairman J. Harvie Wilkinson suggested how the group's presentation to the high state officials should proceed.
    - Correspondence, 1958-1964, 1978, 1980 (Box-folder 252/12-20)
    - Memoranda, 1958-1961, 1980 (Box-folder 252/21)
    - Printed Materials, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 252/22)
  - Virginia Foundation for Independent Colleges 1959-1961 (Box-folder 252/23)
    One folder of correspondence. The topic of most of the letters is fund raising.
  - Virginia State Board of Education 1961-1969
    One foot of correspondence, speeches, subject files, printed materials and clippings from Powell's service on this board. Powell shared the board's interest in many areas including: raising the level of public education, the role of public television in the classroom, continuing education of teachers and research in education. All of these topics are documented here.
    As President of the State Board of Education in the socially tumultuous year of 1968, Powell wrote the pamphlet, "Citizenship Education as Law; Disorder, Extremism and Civil Disobedience." It was published and distributed by the board as part of the Citizenship Education Project initiated by Powell. Included here are correspondence, minutes and documentation of the "Citizenship Education Project."
    As in the Richmond School Board papers, the area of racial desegregation, which formed the backdrop to this entire period, is only lightly documented here. As the Virginia General Assembly had directed the state board to authorize local school boards to resume control of pupil placement, few records concerning desegregation were created by state board members.
    The subject file "Prince Edward County School Board Suit" does involve state board action in desegregation. This file includes a 1961 memorandum prepared by Powell's Hunton & Williams law firm partner George C. Freeman, Jr. This document is notable for two reasons. The topic, "The State Board of Education's Power to Operate Free Public Schools In Localities Where Local School Boards Cannot or Will Not Continue To Operate Them" suggests that Powell considered the idea of circumventing the General Assembly's local school board option policy. The memorandum is also interesting as an early example of the reliance Powell would come to have on his law firm partners in areas beyond the conduct of Hunton & Williams business. In drafting his American Bar Association presidential speeches, in his work on the revision of the Virginia Constitution, and in preparation for hearings on his Supreme Court nomination, the counsel of his law partners informed his public statements and writings.
    On July 1, 1964, Powell was part of the unanimous vote to extend the deadline for state tuition grants for children attending private, all-white schools. His handwritten revisions to the draft of the minutes of this meeting show Powell's anticipation of the criticism that he and the board were to receive for taking this action.
    - Correspondence, 1961-1969 (Box-folder 252/24-32, Box-folder 253/1-35, Box-folder 254/1)
    - Speeches
      - Educational Research, November 1, 1962 (Box-folder 254/2)
      - The Challenge to the Private Preparatory School, January 31, 1967 (Box-folder 254/3)
      - Reflections on the State of Public Education, February 4, 1969 (Box-folder 254/4)
    - Subject Files